Guide to the S. Niewenhous, Inc. Architectural Specifications Collection 1881-1923, undated PR 93
New-York Historical Society
S. Niewenhous, Inc. Architectural Specifications Collection
1881-1923, undated
New-York Historical Society
S. Niewenhous, Inc.
PR 93
1.68 Linear feet (4 boxes)
Collection of architectural specifications and contracts relating to the alteration, expansion, or construction of schools, hospitals, religious institutions, apartment buildings, warehouses and private residences done by S. Niewenhous, Inc. in New York City between 1881 and 1923.
Provenance
Gift of George B. Niewenhous, February 24, 2001.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Historical Note
Siebrand Niewenhous founded his company of builders, S. Niewenhous, Inc., in Manhattan in the late 1870s. After his death in 1914, the presidency of the company was taken over by August Niewenhous. The company worked on construction projects in all five boroughs of New York, many of which were for Roman Catholic organizations. S. Niewenhous, Inc. remained in operation until 1952.
Scope and Content Note
The S. Niewenhous, Inc. Architectural Specifications Collection spans the period from 1881 to 1923 and primarily contains specifications and contracts relating to the alteration, expansion, or construction of schools, hospitals, religious institutions, apartment buildings, warehouses, factories, stables, and private residences in New York City. Some materials are undated. Related correspondence, permits, and detail drawings are also present. Included are specifications by architects I.E. Ditmars, William Schickel, Schickel & Ditmars, Henry A. Koelble, Julius Boekell & Sons, Ditmars & Brite, John H. Friend, Thomas J. Duff, Charles H. Baxter & Co., Michael J. Garvin, John E. Kerby, Julius Kastner, Carl L. Otto, and F. Joseph Untersee.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged into twoseries:
Series I: Institutional Buildings
Series II: Miscellaneous Buildings
Specifications.; Detail drawings.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Design and construction.; Construction contracts.; Hospitals -- New York (State) -- New York -- Design and construction.; Correspondence.; Church buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Design and construction.; Apartment houses -- New York (State) -- New York -- Design and construction.; Contracts.; Charles H. Baxter & Co.; Ditmars & Brite; Ditmars, Isaac Edward, 1850-1934; Duff, Thomas J.; Friend, John H.; Garvin, Michael J., 1861-1918; Julius Boeckell & Sons; Kastner, Julius; Kerby, John E.; Koelble, Henry A.; Otto, Carl L.; Schickel & Ditmars; Schickel, William, 1850-1907; Untersee, F. Joseph
- Series I: Institutional Buildings
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I consists of architectural specifications for projects undertaken for institutions, many of which were associated with the Roman Catholic Church, dating from 1881 to 1918. Materials are arranged by type of institution into four subseries: Charitable Organizations, Churches, Hospitals, and Schools. Thereunder they are arranged alphabetically. All of the buildings are in New York City, with the exception of a project at the Mount St. Alphonsus Seminary in Esopus, New York. Most of the documents in this series relate to alterations or additions made to existing buildings.
  - Charitable Organizations
    - St. Francis Home, Manhattan - 605-617 East 5th Street, 1906-1912 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Society of Catholic Mechanics, Manhattan - East 88th Street near Third Avenue, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Churches
    - Capuchin Fathers Convent, Manhattan -- Stanton and Pitt Streets, 1881 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Church of the Assumption Clubhouse, Manhattan - West 50th Street between Ninth and Tenth Avenues, 1911 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Church of the Immaculate Conception Clubhouse, Bronx, 1907 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mount St. Alphonsus Seminary, Esopus, NY, 1905 1911 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Redemptorist Fathers Clubhouse, Bronx, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - St. Alphonsus Sisters Residence, Manhattan - 14 Thompson Street, 1913 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - St. Alphonsus Rectory, Manhattan - 308 West Broadway, 1913-1918 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - St. Joseph's Asylum Chapel, Manhattan - East 90th Street, 1907 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - St. Joseph's Church Rectory, Manhattan - 421 East 86th Street, 1908 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - St. Mary's Church, Bronx - 150th Street and Melrose Avenue, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    - St. Pious Church and Rectory, Bronx - 145th Street, east of Willis Avenue, 1907 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hospitals
    - German Hospital and Dispensary (currently Lenox Hill Hospital),Manhattan - Park Avenue between East 76th and East 77th Streets, 1910 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
    - Nazareth House of the Sisters of Charity, Bronx - Spuyten Duyvil, 1907 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
    - New York Foundling Hospital, Manhattan - East 67th - 68th Streets, 1909 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
    - St. Anthony's Hospital, Queens - Woodhaven, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    - St. Francis Hospital, Bronx - East 142nd Street, Brook Avenue and St. Ann's Street, 1910 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    - St. Joseph's Hospital, Bronx - 143rd and 144th Streets and Brook Avenue, 1906-1914 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
    - St. Joseph's Hospital, Bronx - 143rd and 144th Streets and Brook Avenue, 1915-1918 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
    - St. Vincent's Hospital, Staten Island, 1908 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Schools
    - Parochial School, Church of Our Lady of Perpetual Help, Manhattan - 62nd Street, between First and Second Avenues, 1906 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    - School of St. Francis of Assisi, Manhattan - 143 West 31st Street, 1911 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
- Series II: Miscellaneous Buildings
  Series II consists of architectural specifications for the erection of or alteration to a variety of buildings including apartment houses, warehouses, office buildings, factories, stables, sheds, and outhouses dating from 1897-1923. Materials are arranged by New York City borough and thereunder by address; miscellaneous and unidentified materials are at the end of the series. Some specifications concern the erection of new buildings, but many relate to minor alterations or additions to existing structures. Where building types are identified in the specifications they are noted in parentheses after the address. Included in this series is one folder of miscellaneous specifications containing sections of documents for unidentified building projects. One folder at the end of the series contains general specifications and detail drawings for such things as roofing and concrete reinforcement.
  - Bronx
    - 526-528 East 142nd Street (apartment house), 1911 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
    - North side of 151st Street west of Melrose Avenue (shed), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
    - 375 East 152nd Street (stable), 1910 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
    - Southwest corner of 156th Street and St. Ann's Avenue (apartment house), 1901-1903 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 27)
    - 188th Street and The Concourse, southeast corner (garage), 1914 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 28)
    - Third Avenue near 148th Street (office building), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 29)
    - Third Avenue and East 156th Street, northeast corner, 1909 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
    - 2311-3219 Beaumont Avenue (apartment house), 1912 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
    - 640 Courtlandt Avenue, 1916 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
    - 2960 Jerome Avenue (house), 1913 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
    - Mt. Eden Avenue near Jerome Avenue (garage), 1923 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
    - 756 Union Boulevard (store), 1910 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Willis Avenue and Southern Boulevard, 1910 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
  - Brooklyn
    - East side of Banker Street south of Norman Avenue (stable), 1916-1919 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
    - 616 Bedford Avenue, 1909 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Manhattan -- Named Streets and Avenues
    - 46 Allen Street (outhouse), 1905 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 39)
    - 47 Ann Street, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
    - Audubon Avenue and West 168th Street, southwest corner (apartment house), 1909 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 41)
    - 184 Bowery (loft building), 1910 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 42)
    - 174 Essex Street (apartment house), 1905 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 43)
    - 1585 Madison Avenue, 1915 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 44)
    - 41 North Moore Street (warehouse, store), 1897, 1902 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 45)
  - Manhattan -- Numbered Avenues
    - 54-56 Third Avenue (business building), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 46)
    - 793 Third Avenue (store), 1906 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 47)
    - 1234-1238 Third Avenue (apartment building), 1900-1922 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 48)
    - 413 Fifth Avenue (house), 1903 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 49)
    - 412 Eighth Avenue (office building), 1914 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 50)
    - Eighth Avenue and 125th Street, northwest corner, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 51)
    - 220-222 Ninth Avenue, 1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 52)
  - Manhattan -- Numbered Streets
    - 16 East 3rd Street (house), 1907 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 53)
    - 203-209 East 9th Street (apartment building), 1910-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 54)
    - 608-610 East 18th Street (factory), 1909 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 55)
    - 436-438 East 19th Street (factory), 1904 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 56)
    - 37 East 29th Street, 1922 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 57)
    - 238-240 West 53rd Street (factory), 1914 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 58)
    - 215 West 53rd Street (factory), 1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 59)
    - 244 West 53rd Street (garage), 1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 60)
    - North side of East 58th Street east of Madison Avenue, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 61)
    - 421 East 86th Street (house), 1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 62)
    - 129 East 91st Street (residence), 1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 63)
    - 50 East 92nd Street (residence), 1897 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 64)
    - 312-314 East 92nd Street (laundry), 1919 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 65)
    - 4 West 121st Street (residence), 1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 66)
    - 18 East 126th Street, 1920 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 67)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Unidentified locations, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 68)
    - General specifications, 1910, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 69)